Rabbi Hans S. Bodenheimer Collection 0012.001.005b
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Rabbi Hans S. Bodenheimer
1933-1999
0012.001.005b
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
8.0 Cubic feet 3 archival boxes of documents 1 oversize box of documents several folders of photographs, filed with People photographs 2 boxes of artifacts
Rabbi Hans S. Bodenheimer (1913-1999) was born in Bad Nauheim Germany and emigrated to the United States in 1939. In 1942 he and a group of German immigrants founded Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh “New Hope” in Hartford, where he served as Rabbi until his retirement. After meeting in borrowed space for many years, the Congregation’s first building was dedicated in 1956. In 1971, following a series of anti-Semitic acts in Hartford, the congregation built a new synagogue in Bloomfield. Bodenheimer and his future wife, Alma, barely survived Kristallnacht in 1938. Bodenheimer was arrested and deported to Buchenwald where he was held for five weeks and then released. Prior to the Wansee Convention of 1942 that led to the “Final Solution,” Jewish detainees were often held in custody for a period of time and then released. Although Bodenheimer’s captivity predated the advent of the extermination camps, his experiences at Buchenwald were both horrific and traumatic. In 1939 he was granted a visa and came to the United States. Besides his rabbinical duties, Bodenheimer had many other interests and talents. He served as chaplain to the Bloomfield Fire Department, and was one of the few people in the United Sates qualified to repair Torah scrolls. The collection consists primarily of material related to the founding and growth of congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh. A small amount of more personal material is also included. Bodenheimer's autobiography From Bad Nauheim to Bloomfield: My Journey of Faith details his life in both Germany and the United States. There is some overlap between the contents of the Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh and Bodenheimer Collections. Researchers should consult both collections.
Bodenheimer, Hans, Rabbi, Germany; Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh; Holocaust
- Series I: Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Anniversaries/10th, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Anniversaries/20th, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Anniversaries/25th, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Anniversaries/35th, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Anniversaries/40th, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Anniversaries/45th, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Anniversaries/50th, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Book of fundraising tickets for Synagogue, 1950s, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Buildings, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Buildings, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Cemetery, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Chanukah parties, 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Constitution and by-laws, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Midrasha, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Newsletter, 1940s, 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Newsletter, 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Plays for children by Mrs. Bodenheimer, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Religious School/Graduation program, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Religious School/Hartford Bar Mitzvah News, edited by Rev. and Mrs. Hans S. Bodenheimer, 1940s?, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Religious School/Merger with Beth Hillel and Beth Ahm, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Religious School/Samaritan Genesis, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Religious School/Yearbooks, 1960s-1970s, 1960-1979 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Sisterhood, undated (Box 1)
  - Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh/Trees for Israel, undated (Box 1)
- Series II: Synagogues, Miscellaneous and A-G
  - Synagogues/Beth David Synagogue, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Beth El, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Beth Hillel Synagogue, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Congregation Agudas Achim, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Congregation Beth Israel, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Congregation Chevrah Lomdai Mishnayes, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Congregation Teferes Israel, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Emanuel Synagogue, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Emanuel Synagogue/Burial of Torah scrolls destroyed by arson, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Temple Beth Tefilah, undated (Box 2)
  - Synagogues/Temple Beth Torah, undated (Box 2)
  - Awards, undated (Box 2)
  - Benevolent Organizations/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Biographical/From Bad Nauheim to Bloomfield: My Journey of Faith by Rabbi Hans S. Bodenheimer, 1999, undated (Box 2)
  - Biographical/Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 2)
  - Bodenheimer, Alma R. (wife), undated (Box 2)
  - Cemetery, B'nai Israel, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence/Dodd, Thomas J., undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence/Reagan, Ronald, undated (Box 2)
  - Documents/Israelitischer Oberrat Stuttgart (Jewish Municipality of Stuttgart), 1936, folder of communications in German (Box 2)
  - Ephemera/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Events/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Greater Hartford Rabbinic Fellowship/Correspondence, undated (Box 2)
  - Greater Hartford Rabbinic Fellowship/Members, undated (Box 2)
  - Greater Hartford Rabbinic Fellowship/minutes, undated (Box 2)
  - Greater Hartford Rabbinic Fellowship/Projects/Funeral Practices, undated (Box 2)
  - Greater Hartford Rabbinic Fellowship/Projects/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
- Series III: H-Z
  - Holocaust, undated (Box 3)
  - Holocaust/Warsaw Uprising, undated (Box 3)
  - Interfaith, undated (Box 3)
  - Israel, undated (Box 3)
  - Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous/In German, undated (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings/Burning of the Books, in German, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings/German language, undated (Box 3)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 3)
  - Olympics/memorial to 1972 Hostages, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Rabbinical Assembly Manual, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Speeches and Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Yeshiva of Hartford, undated (Box 3)
  - Wiesel, Elie\Two Images: One Destiny, pamphlet issued by United Jewish Appeal, undated (Box 3)
- Oversize
  - Certificate awarded to Rabbi Bodenheimer on 25th anniversary of congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh, undated
  - Citation from Connecticut General Assembly, 1996
  - Drawing of Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh, 1968
- Artifacts
  - Carved nameplate for desk, undated
  - Tefflin bags, undated
  - B'nai B'rith pin, undated
  - Commemorative medal dated 1985
  - 2 white kepah, undated
  - Bell, decorated, undated
  - 2 small decorative boxes, undated
  - Money collection can, undated
  - Wall hanging of word "Shalom" from Israel, undated
  - Wimple, undated
  - 4 shofars, undated
  - Jug from Holland, undated
  - Sabbath lamp, undated